<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<queries>
	<query>
		<title>Support towards the Europe PMC initiative-Contribution for 2014-2016</title>
		<objective> "The proposed action will provide continued support to the European Research Council (ERC) in the implementation of its Open Access strategy for projects funded in the Life Sciences domain. It follows on from the project ""Support towards the Europe PMC initiative-Contribution for 2013""(ERC-EuropePMC-SUP-2013) which has allowed the ERC to offer the benefits of Europe PMC to its funded researchers for the first time in 2013. The ERC Open Access strategy, and how the present project will assist the ERC in its implementation, is explained below"</objective>
		<identifier>H2020Adhoc201420</identifier>
	</query>
	<query>
		<title>OPtimising thERapy to prevent Avoidable hospital admissions in the Multimorbid elderly</title>
		<objective>Most older adults have multiple chronic diseases (multimorbidity) and multiple medications (polypharmacy). However, multimorbid patients are often excluded from clinical trials and most guidelines address diseases in isolation. Inappropriate drug prescription and poor drug compliance are common and contribute to up to 30% of hospital admissions. OPERAM investigators developed STOPP/START criteria to detect inappropriate drug use, both over- and underuse. Applying these criteria limits unnecessary polypharmacy and reduces underuse of indicated medications, but it remains uncertain whether systematic pharmacotherapy optimisation can improve clinical outcomes and reduce costs.We propose a multicentre randomised controlled trial to assess the impact of a userfriendly software-assisted intervention to optimise pharmacotherapy and to enhance compliance in 1900 multimorbid patients aged ≥75 years. Outcomes will include drug-related hospital admissions, health care utilisation, quality of life, patient preferences and cost-effectiveness. We will also perform several network meta-analyses (NMA) to provide new comparative evidence on the most effective and safest pharmacological and non-pharmacological interventions to reduce common causes of preventable hospital admissions (e.g. falls, fractures, bleeding). Therapy optimisation in the multimorbid elderly, enhanced compliance and discontinuation of less effective interventions have the potential to improve clinical, quality of life and safety outcomes, while reducing costs. We will provide a structured method with practical software solutions for optimal prescribing and new comparative evidence from NMAs for addressing multimorbidity and polypharmacy by means of customised, patient-centred guidelines. OPERAM ultimately aims at better healthcare delivery in primary and hospital care, based on effective, safe, personalised and cost-effective interventions that can be applied to the rapidly growing older population in Europe.</objective>
		<identifier>H2020PHC2014twostage</identifier>
	</query>
	<query>
		<title>Elimination of Senescent Cells Approach for treatment of COPD</title>
		<objective>Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD) is estimated to affect up to 600 million people worldwide and by 2020 it will become the third most frequent cause of death. In Europe alone, COPD affects up to 10% of people (i.e. more people than breast cancer and diabetes) and it takes the life of around 300,000 Europeans each year. Current therapies are associated with a variety of side effects some of which can be acute and even life threatening. Moreover, none of the existing medications for COPD has been shown conclusively to modify the long-term decline in lung function thus, COPD remains a disease with a significant unmet medical need.
		Our approach is focusing on the pharmacological elimination of senescent cells (i.e. cells that have stopped dividing, but do affect their microenvironment) which accumulate in tissues with age and contribute to multiple age-related diseases, including COPD. In particular, we recently discovered that with the use of a particular molecule, we could efficiently target the molecular mechanisms that are responsible for the viability of senescent cells, leading to specific elimination of these cells from tissues. In turn, the goal of the PoC project is two-fold. (1) The first goal is to establish the technical feasibility of our idea by testing the effect of the identified molecule on the disease development and progression using the COPD mouse model we developed. (2) The second goal is to establish the business feasibility of our revolutionary approach by taking the necessary steps towards its commercialization, focusing on the creation of strategic alliances with key private sector companies.</objective>
        <identifier>ERC2016PoC</identifier>
	</query>
	<query>
		<title>Synthesizing Meiotic Crossover Hotspots in Arabidopsis</title>
		<objective>The majority of eukaryotes reproduce sexually via meiosis. During meiosis homologous chromosomes pair and undergo reciprocal genetic exchange termed crossover. Meiotic recombination is a major evolutionary force and has a profound effect on patterns of genetic diversity in sexual species. Crossovers distributions are highly non-random and are typically focused in narrow hotspots. Study of hotspots throughout eukaryotes has revealed combinations of genetic and epigenetic factors that contribute to their distributions. In this proposal we will use the extensive genetics and genomics tools available in Arabidopsis to comprehensively dissect hotspot patterning. The strategic aim of the proposal is to use this knowledge to direct de novo hotspots to loci of choice. In the first aim we will use functional genomics to profile the chromosomal distributions of key recombination proteins and test the role of chromatin and higher-order structures in driving these patterns. In the second aim we will study individual hotspots at the fine-scale, to the resolution of individual polymorphisms, using amplification and sequencing of recombinant molecules from gamete DNA. To test genetic versus epigenetic control of hotspots we will use genome-editing to delete hotspot-associated CTT-repeat DNA sequence motifs, in addition to directing DNA methylation in order to epigenetically silence recombination. In the final aim we will use our combined knowledge of hotspot control to implement genome-editing technologies (TALENs &amp; CRISPR-Cas9) during meiosis. This will allow us to rationally control hotspot locations, which will be definitive proof that our models for recombination control are correct. This technology will also accelerate breeding and genome-engineering of our most important crops, where recombination can be limiting. Finally, mapping hotspots will allow us to better understand patterns of natural genetic diversity, including detecting the signatures of selection.</objective>
        <identifier>ERC2015CoG</identifier>
	</query>
	<query>
		<title>Transgenerational transmission of maternal childhood trauma and its sequelae – Altered maternal physiology during pregnancy and implications for newborn neurodevelopment</title>
		<objective>Alarming statistics in a recent report by the EU Agency for Fundamental Rights suggest that 1 in 3 women have experienced physical or sexual violence in childhood. The sequelae of childhood trauma (CT) exposure include psychopathology, altered stress physiology, obesity, and increased likelihood of exposure to violence in adulthood. Also, emerging evidence suggests the long shadow cast by CT may be transmitted to the offspring of exposed individuals, who have a higher prevalence of psychiatric disorders. To date, potential pathways of transgenerational transmission have focused on the offspring’s exposure to unfavorable conditions in postnatal life (i.e., suboptimal parenting behaviors). However, it is likely that transgenerational transmission of the effects of maternal CT may start during fetal life. It is well established that CT produces endocrine and immunological dysregulation, and the persistence of such dysregulation during pregnancy may affect fetal brain development to confer increased risk for psychopathology. Despite its plausibility, fetal programming has not yet been studied as a potential transmission pathway of the effects of CT from mother to child. In this proposed prospective, longitudinal study, 200 mother-child dyads will be followed from early gestation till the neonatal period. Serial measures of stress-related endocrine (CRH, cortisol) and immune (CRP, IL-6) biology will be collected in early, mid and late gestation. At birth newborn MRI scans will be acquired to quantify volumes and connectivity of fronto-limbic brain regions. The proposed study will address specific hypotheses about the transgenerational transmission during gestation of the effects of maternal CT on her child’s brain and the role of maternal-placental-fetal endocrine and immune biology as a mediator of this effect. Study findings may suggest new avenues for development of prevention and intervention strategies to limit the transgenerational perpetuation of poor health.</objective>
		<identifier>ERC2014STG</identifier>
	</query>
</queries>
